Guide to the Elizabeth Wiegand papers, 1926-1969.
Wiegand, Elizabeth papers, 1926-1969
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Elizabeth Wiegand papers, 1926-1969.
23-18-1242
Elizabeth Wiegand, 1916-
5 cubic ft.
Conference programs, speeches, bulletins, correspondence, and other papers.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Includes bound volumes of conference progams, speeches, and bulletins; bound and unbound bulletins on household economics and management; correspondence about budgeting, records of adult home management programs; and other papers of Elizabeth Wiegand related to her career on the faculty of the New York State College of Home Economics.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Professor of household economics and household management, New York State College of Home Economics at Cornell University.
Elizabeth Wiegand graduated from Cornell in 1938, worked several years as a home demonstration agent in county extension programs in New York State, and returned to Cornell, receiving her M.A. (1949) and Ph.D. (1953). Her doctoral dissertation on the use of time by New York State homemakers provided not only descriptive data but the basis for quantifying their work contributions with current data. She was involved in teaching and research at Michigan State University for three years following completion of her Ph.D. Upon her return to Cornell, she moved through the ranks of assistant professor (1957) to professor (1964) as an extension specialist in family economics and home management. She was named professor emerita in 1981.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Includes bound volumes of conference progams, speeches, and bulletins; bound and unbound bulletins on household economics and management; correspondence about budgeting, answered by Helen Canon (1927-1947), Jean Warren (1953-1964), Elizabeth Wiegand (1959-1969), and other faculty members (1948-1952); records of adult home management programs; and other papers of Elizabeth Wiegand related to her career on the faculty of the New York State College of Home Economics (now the College of Human Ecology).
SUBJECTS
Names:
Wiegand, Elizabeth, 1916-; Canon, Helen, b. 1888.; Warren, Jean.; New York State College of Home Economics.; New York State College of Human Ecology.
Subjects:
Home economics.; Home economics--Study and teaching.; College teachers.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
CONTAINER LIST
- 2 bound volumes of Economic Conference Programs, 1951-1955, 1956-1962 (Box 1)
- 2 bound volumes of Studies of Income and Expenditures, 1939-1950, 1954-1958 (Box 1)
- 1 bound volume of bulletins on Studies of Income and Expenditures (by Cornell, other colleges, or U.S. Department of Agriculture), 1931-1962 (Box 1)
- 1 bound volume of National Home Laundry Conferences (program and speeches), 1951-1960 (Box 1)
- 1 separate issue, 1963 (Box 1)
- 2 bound volumes, Plan of Work for the Extension Program of this Department, 1926-1945, 1946-1950 (Box 1)
- 1 spirally bound volume, 1961-1969 (Box 1)
- 3 bound volumes of Kitchen Planning Bulletins (Cornell, other colleges of U.S. Department of Agriculture, 1906-1929, 1930-1939, 1940-1959 (Box 2)
- "The Convenient Kitchen" (roll), 1927 (Box 2)
- 1 volume, Bulletins on Kitchen Storage (Cornell, other colleges or U.S. Department of Agriculture), 1932-1961 (Box 2)
- Some unbound bulletins and mimeos, ca. 1946-1963 (Box 2)
- Some teaching outlines on storage (Box 2)
- Some unbound bulletins and mimeos on Clothing Storage, 1935-1962 (Box 2)
- Some teaching outlines on clothes storage (Box 2)
- 1 large bound volume on House Cleaning, 1935-1959 (Box 2)
- A "clutch" of teaching outlines on house cleaning and work simplification (Box 2)
- Some unbound volumes on Care of Floors, 1955-1963 (Box 2)
- 3 unbound bulletins on Care of Rugs and Upholstery, 1944-1962 (Box 2)
- Some teaching outlines on floors, rugs and upholstery (Box 2)
- 1 bound volume of bulletins on Home Laundering (Cornell, other colleges of U.S. Department of Agriculture), 1929-1961 (Box 2)
- Some teaching outlines on laundering and stain removal (Box 2)
- 1 bound volume of bulletins on Ironing (Cornell, other colleges), 1943-1953 (Box 2)
- Some teaching outlines on ironing (Box 2)
- 1 bound volume on bulletins on Work Simplification (other colleges or commercial organizations), 1928-1956 (Box 2)
- 1 bound volume on Home and Time Management and Work Simplification, 1939-1955 (Box 2)
- 1 bound volume of bulletins on Household Management, 1938-1961 (Box 2)
- Some unbound materials on household management, 1943-1959 (Box 2)
- 1 bound volume on Time Studies, 1927-1957 (Box 2)
- Some unbound bulletins and mimeos, ca. 1942-1954 (Box 2)
- Account books, 1917-1957 (Box 3)
- Bound volume of pamphlets on budgets from commercial and college sources, 1917-1954 (Box 3)
- Bound volume of bulletins on children and money from commercial and college sources, 1944-1960 (Box 3)
- Bound volume of publications prepared by the Institute of Life Insurance, 1947-1961 (Box 3)
- Folders of correspondence about budgeting
  - Answered by Dr. Helen Canon, head of this department, 1927-1947 (Box 3)
  - Answered by several members of department, 1948-1952 (Box 3)
  - Mostly answered by Dr. Elizabeth Wiegand, 1959-1969 (Box 3)
- Programs about consumer marketing by Professor Lucille Williamson in miscellaneous counties from Albany to Rensselaer (Box 4)
- Home Management Programs for 4-H clubs conducted by various extension specialists in counties--Albany through Yates (Box 4)
- Home Management Programs for adults--Albany County through Essex County, 1961-1969 (Box 4)
- Home Management Programs for adults--Franklin County through Yates County, 1961-1969 (Box 5)